"The Best Way to Cook Vegetables"
You may remember
when I compared the effects
of different cooking methods
on different phytonutrients
in bell peppers, mushrooms,
and a few other veggies.
Well, food scientists
have outdone themselves
in this study.
They looked at six
different cooking methods
on 20 different vegetables,
comparing three
distinct measures
of antioxidant activity.
That's more than 300
separate experiments
to figure out the best way
to cook our vegetables.
First, though,
let's figure out the worst
in terms of loss
of antioxidant content.
Consider boiling, microwaving,
pressure-cooking in water,
griddling, like cooking
in a frying pan without oil,
frying in a frying pan,
and baking at about 400 degrees
Fahrenheit (200°C).
What's your guess
for the worst?
The worst is boiling
when it comes
to losing antioxidants.
The second worst?
Boiling under pressure.
When we use
wet cooking methods,
some of the nutrition is lost
into the cooking water;
when it comes
to preparing vegetables
with their antioxidants
in mind,
water is not
a cook's best friend.
But how bad is bad?
It may be less than you think.
Averaging
over those 20 vegetables,
boiling only removes about
14 percent of the antioxidants.
So, if you really like
boiled broccoli, fine,
just eat one more floret.
Seven florets
of boiled broccoli
has all the antioxidant power
of six florets
of raw broccoli.
So, the best way
to eat your veggies
is really whichever way
will get you to eat
the most of them,
with the exception of frying,
which not only adds
empty calories
but also toxic byproducts
that are produced
when oils are heated
to frying temperatures.
What's the gentlest
cooking method?
The one that preserves
the most antioxidants?
Microwaving, which preserves
more than 97 percent
of the antioxidants.
One vegetable has antioxidants
that can really get clobbered,
no matter how you cook it,
losing up to 75 percent
of its antioxidant capacity.
What's the one vegetable
that's really best eaten raw?
Was it artichoke hearts,
asparagus, beets,
broad beans
(also known as fava beans),
broccoli,
I hope we don't have to eat
raw Brussels sprouts,
cauliflower, carrots, celery,
eggplant, garlic, green beans,
leeks, corn on the cob,
onions, peas, bell peppers,
spinach, Swiss chard,
or zucchini?
The most vulnerable vegetable
is the bell pepper.
So, I try to eat those raw
or add them right at the end
of whatever I'm cooking,
like pasta sauce,
so they really just
kind of get warmed up
without really being cooked.
On the other hand,
three vegetables
are hardly affected
by cooking at all.
You could even boil them
and still retain
nearly all their antioxidants.
Can you guess
at least one of the three?
They're artichokes, beets,
and onions.
Boil away.
Asparagus gets
an honorable mention here.
It's pretty much unaffected
by any cooking method
except frying,
so you can boil asparagus, too.
Final question, and perhaps
the most interesting,
there are two vegetables that,
no matter what you do to them,
tend to increase
in antioxidant value.
They may become even healthier
upon cooking.
Which two are they?
First, the runner-up:
green beans.
With the exception of boiling
and pressure cooking,
they actually increase
in antioxidant power
when cooked,
so microwaved green beans
have more antioxidants
than raw.
And tied for first?
Which two vegetables
nearly always increase in value,
no matter how you cook them?
Carrots and celery.
So, when we make
a nice vegetable soup,
we can actually boost
their nutrition.
One vegetable
that wasn't covered
was one of my favorites: kale.
As I discuss in my video
How to Cook Greens,
kale can be cooked
by blanching or steaming
to boost antioxidants.
It can even be boiled
and not lose
antioxidant nutrition.